Good morning. Today's דף *daf* is מ"ט *mem-tet* and we actually pick
up on the very first word of מ"ט *mem-tet*. And what we're
discussing is the significance of the various acts of the חפינה chafina
*chafina* and leading into the putting of the קטורת ketoret *ketoret*. So,
the taking of the קטורת ketoret? *ketoret* from the original container to
the hand-breadths and the putting it into the ladle, and then the
conveying of it. Those are three steps. And those three steps to
some degree parallel three steps by a מנחה Mincha *mincha* and three
steps by a normal קרבן korban. *korban*: שחיטה shechita, *shechita*, the separating
off of the parts that are going to be put ritually and
the parts that are left behind, the placing of the blood in
the vessels, so the transferring of the hand-breadths to the vessel, and
then the conveying of the blood to the altar and here the
conveying of it to the קדש קדשים *kodesh kodashim*. So the גמרא
gemara *gemara* raises interesting questions about whether you actually have to do
a חפינה chafina *chafina* with your hands, can you use a vessel
to do the חפינה chafina *chafina*. But nevertheless, all of yesterday's דף
*daf* seemed to treat חפינה chafina *chafina* as a very significant ritual,
and a necessary ritual for it to be placed and used, and
had various discussions exactly what's the normal way of doing it. More
significantly, the discussions that came up in the גמרא gemara *gemara* was
the issue about let's say something spills from the time of the
חפינה chafina. *chafina* until it's put into the vessel. Is that considered
to be a problem or not? Is it like blood spills on
the ground? Is the hands that is containing the קטורת ketoret. *ketoret*
like the throat of the animal, is what the גמרא gemara *gemara*
says. Very visual, also the idea of the קטורת ketoret *ketoret* being
a מכפר *mechaper* and functioning like blood. But also what it's doing
is it's underscoring the way in which these עבודות avodot *avodot*, like
the עבודה avoda. *avoda* of הדם *hadam*.
And the reason that that was a question more than, for example,
the issue of the spilling of the קומץ *kometz* of the מנחה
*mincha*, which was taken for granted, was pointed out by the תוספות
ישנים Tosafot Yeshanim. *Tosafot Yeshanim* and by תוספות tosafot. *Tosafot* that there
are two differences. Here number one, the use of the placing of
it in the vessel is not as much of an עבודה avoda,
*avoda*, that was more necessity as a way of conveying, not as
much of an עבודה avoda *avoda* as we saw before. And the
actual taking of it from the container of the original קטורת ketoret
*ketoret* wasn't doing the exact same thing because it wasn't like leaving
behind a part that could not be used the same way separating
what goes on the altar from what doesn't go on the altar.
It's not the same way that that's true in the case as
it is by שחיטה shechita *shechita*. So that raised the question of
to what degree are these considered right עבודות Avodot *avodot* and have
their parallel. But nevertheless the גמרא gemara: *gemara*,
you know, at the end of the day there did not actually
have a black conclusion, but then moved on to say that even
during the act of חפינה chafina *chafina* you could have a thought
of פיגול *pigul*, which also seems to say that it's very much
an עבודה avoda *avoda*. Based on that, the רמב"ם *Rambam* says this
act is an act of עבודה avoda, *avoda*. So, so that finally
got us to the question at the end of yesterday, which is
so much thinking about this as an עבודה avoda *avoda*, and not
only can we transfer requirements that we know are done by blood
to this act of חפינה chafina? *chafina*, but maybe take a leniency
by the חפינה chafina? *chafina* and assume that it also applies back
to blood. So now the question moves from the חפינה chafina. *chafina*
and the placing in the vessel to the conveyance of it into
the קדש קדשים *kodesh kodashim*, the הולכה holacha, *holacha*. And the גמרא
gemara. *gemara*'s question is, can הולכה holacha, *holacha* of the blood be
done with the left hand? And the evidence is, well, you do
the conveyance in the left hand, you should be able to do
the הולכה holacha *holacha* of blood in the left hand. And that
actually was where the גמרא Gemara, *gemara* concluded yesterday, that maybe the
conveyance of blood could be done with the left hand just like
the conveyance of the קטורת ketoret? *ketoret*, again assuming this equation in
parallel. So with that we pick up here now at the top
of מ"ט עמוד א *mem-tet amud aleph*. So let's take a look.
מיתיבי *Meitivei*, they ask you on this assertion that you can do
הולכה holacha? *holacha* of blood with the left hand. We have a
ברייתא baraita *braita* that says the following: זר zar ואונן שיכור ובעל
מום *zar ve-onen shikkor u-va'al mum*. The following four people who are
not allowed to do the service: a non-כהן kohen *kohen*, an אונן
*onen*, a כהן kohen *kohen* who has an immediate loss of an
immediate relative on the day of that loss, שיכור
*shikkor*, a כהן kohen *kohen* who is drunk, either discussion of רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות tosafot *Tosafot* either through a minimum amount of
wine or even maybe through other intoxicating beverages, right,
and בעל מום *ba'al mum*, a כהן Kohen *kohen* with a blemish.
So there's clear places in the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* where all of
that is forbidden to do the עבודה avodah *avoda*, and the גמרא
gemara *gemara* understands and learns out elsewhere that if it's forbidden to
do the עבודה avodah? *avoda*, it invalidates the עבודה avoda, *avoda* if
a כהן Kohen *kohen* in that state does it, or that type
of a כהן Kohen *kohen* does it. So here are the types
of עבודות *avodot* that that כהן Kohen, *kohen* could invalidate: בקבלה *be-kabbala*,
catching the blood, ובהולכה *u-ve-holacha*, conveying the blood, ובזריקה *bi-zerika*, and throwing
the blood, פסול pasul, *pasul*, is invalid. The only thing it didn't
mention is of the four classic עבודות *avodot* is שחיטה shechitah, *shechita*
because that is כשר בזר *kasher be-zar*. Okay, now, one minute. What,
as a זר zar *zar*? Yeah, okay, so that we don't know,
we know שחיטה shechita. *shechita* is כשר בזר *kasher be-zar*. Is it
כשר באונן *kasher be-onen*, is it כשר בשיכור *kasher be-shikkor*, presumably it's
כשר בבעל מום *kasher be-ba'al mum* if it's כשר בזר *kasher be-zar*.
But okay, we're not here to look at שחיטה shechita, *shechita*, just
point out that that's not in the list. But now... Okay, but
just because if the כהן Kohen has a personal status, a problematic
status it invalidates, doesn't mean that using the left hand invalidates. But
then the ברייתא baraita goes on. וכן יושב, V'chen yoshev, similarly if
he's sitting, we know a כהן Kohen, has to stand when doing
the עבודה. avoda וכן שמאל, V'chen smol, and if he uses the
left hand. So it's an explicit ברייתא baraita? that the use of
the left hand invalidates not only the קבלה, kabbala, not only the
הולכה, holacha, not only the קבלה, kabbala, not only the זריקה, zrika,
but even the הולכה, holacha even the conveyance. So גמרא gemara. says:
פסול, pasul. all this is invalid. תיובתא, Tyufta, you're right, that's an
absolute contradiction to what we said yesterday, that you could do the
הולכה holacha, in the right, in the left hand. So now the
גמרא gemara says: one minute, if yesterday that was the question asked
of רב ששת Rav Sheshet and רב ששת Rav Sheshet basically tried
to argue based on the קטורת ketoret. that it was good. So
how could רב ששת Rav Sheshet not have known of this ברייתא?
baraita. We actually know that רב ששת Rav Sheshet did know of
this ברייתא. baraita So גמרא gemara says: ורב ששת הוא דאותבה. ve-Rav
Sheshet hu d'otva. רב ששת Rav Sheshet in another context used this
ברייתא baraita that we just quoted to challenge a different position. So
how could רב ששת Rav Sheshet have concluded, said that you can
convey in the left hand? Here is a ברייתא baraita. explicitly you
can't. One minute, and we know that רב ששת Rav Sheshet knows
of this ברייתא. baraita? How do we know רב ששת Rav Sheshet
knows of this ברייתא? braita דאמר ליה רב ששת לאמוראיה דרב חסדא.
D'amar lei Rav Sheshet l'amoraei d'Rav Chisda. רב ששת Rav Sheshet said
to the אמורא amora of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. An אמורא amora
used this way means basically the loudspeaker, the announcer, meaning there's the
people we call the אמוראים, Amoraim, which are all the named great
rabbis of the גמרא: gemara רבינא, Ravina, רב אשי, Rav Ashi, רב
ששת, Rav Sheshet, רבא, Rava, אביי. Abaye. And there's the תנאים, Tannaim,
right? רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. That's like what I call sometimes capital A אמורא Amora and
capital T תנא. Tana. But then there's these other functions which I
would call lower A אמורא, amora, lower T תנא, tana, which is
the people that actually did an assisting type of a job to
the אמוראים Amoraim and the תנאים. Tannaim. So אמורא amora used in
this context does not mean the author of these positions. It means
somebody that he would take along with them and basically he would
whisper to him, this is before the age of microphones. He was
a great שבס Shabbos microphone. Before electricity, you would whisper to your
אמורא, amora, you'd tell your אמורא amora what you needed said and
then he would yell it out to the crowd. Okay? That would
be considered the אמורא, amora, lowercase אמורא amora is the one that
would publicize and announce it and yell it to the crowd. Similarly
a תנא, tana, although here it's more about memorization and less about
volume, is a תנא tana would be in the age of an
oral tradition and before publishing in books in the written word. How
would you publish something? Like when we say רבי Rebbi wrote or
edited the משנה, Mishna, he did not put pen to paper in
the writing of the משנה. Mishna. There was no written משנה Mishna
in the time of רבי. Rebbi. What רבי Rebbi did was is
determine a fixed text based on other fixed texts, fixed texts meaning
a fixed oral text, based on other fixed oral traditions. And then
he, after he fixed the text, he'd call in a group of
תנאים, Tannaim, memorizers and תנא, tana, repeaters, the word תנא tana is
to repeat, repeaters. He'd take them all in, he'd say 'here's the
text', and he'd give it to them verbally and they would repeat
and they would memorize it. And then he would send them out
to all the different cities and towns and they would teach it
over exactly word for word. And that's how you would, it was
not written. That, when was it written? Probably we don't know exactly
when the earliest writings were, probably at the beginning of the גאונים
Geonic period. Although there's arguments about different pieces of tannaitic material that
might have been earlier, like the ספרא, Sifra, like the מגילת תענית,
Megillat Taanit, whatever. Anyway, so a תנא tana would be a repeater,
a memorizer and a repeater as Saul Lieberman said, you wanted one
with a great memory and very little creativity because you don't want
them inserting their own styles in it. And an אמורא amora also
from the word like אמור amur would be somebody who would say
over, but here not to memorize but here to announce. So that's
what an אמורא amora is. Back to our גמרא. gemara בעי מיני
מרב חסדא, Ba'i minei me-Rav Chisda, so now, דאמר ליה רב ששת
לאמוראיה דרב חסדא. d'amar lei Rav Sheshet l'amoraei d'Rav Chisda. So רב
ששת Rav Sheshet said to the אמורא amora of רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, בעי מיני מרב חסדא, ba'i minei me-Rav Chisda,
so this אמורא amora did not necessarily wasn't a תלמיד חכם, talmid
chacham, but he had good access to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. So
he said next time you see רב חסדא Rav Chisda ask him
the following question. הולכה בזר מהו? Holacha be-zar mahu? What's the story
about whether a non-כהן Kohen can do the הולכה? holacha, Okay? Is
it acceptable? The same way a non-כהן Kohen. could do the שחיטה,
shechita? maybe he could do the הולכה, holacha. especially since as I
said yesterday הולכה holacha. is considered a מלאכה שאפשר לבטלה. melacha she-efshar
levatla. It's a type of a מלאכה melacha that in theory you
don't have to have because if you do the שחיטה shechita right
near the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So he wanted to know, the same way
we discussed yesterday הולכה בשמאל, holacha b'smol, he wanted to have this
question asked
of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said
back to him, presumably without asking רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, he maybe
said back to him
immediately, or it's not clear, maybe he said back to him after
asking רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Anyway, כשרה, keshera, no, or it's not
clear. ומקרא מסייעני, Umikra mesayeini, I have a פסוק pasuk that supports
me that a non-זר zar, can do the—a non-כהן Kohen, can do
the הולכה, holacha because what does it say in דברי הימים? Divrei
HaYamim? וישחטו הפסח, Vayishchetu hapesach, they—the owners—slaughtered the פסח. pesach. ויזרקו הכהנים
מידם, Vayizreku hakohanim miyadam, the כהנים kohanim threw the blood from their
hand—their hand—the hands of the owners,
והלוים מפשיטים, vehaleviyim mafshitim, and the לויים Leviyim would flay the
animals. So, if they would throw the blood from the hands of
the owners, meaning—not literally hands, but meaning the owners were holding the
vessels that held the blood. So, they did the הולכה, holacha? because
now you are standing near the מזבח, mizbeach, you're throwing the blood
with the vessel. Who's handing it to you? The owner. So of
course that's also a little bit funny because you need a כהן
Kohen. to do the קבלה, kabbalah, that's not debated. Right. So the
owner does the שחיטה, shechita. the כהן kohen does the קבלה, kabbalah,
gives it back to the owner, presumably, the owner then brings it
to the other כהן, kohen and the כהן kohen throws. So you
see that the זר zar is doing the הולכה. holacha, Okay, so
that's what the אמורא Amora said back, either after having asked רב
ששת Rav Sheshet or רב חסדא Rav Chisda or even without asking
him. ומוסיף רב ששת, Umosif Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet then
challenged him and said, "How could you say that? We have a
ברייתא braita, that says: זר ואונן שיכור ובעל מום בקבלה ובהולכה ובזריקה
פסול, Zar veonen shikur ubaal mum bekabbalah uveholacha uvezrikah pasul,
all the people we mentioned before—a non-כהן, Kohen a mourner, whatever, first
day of the mourning, a drunk, and somebody with a blemish, all
those people cannot do either the קבלה kabbalah catching the blood, the
conveyance, or the throwing. וכן יושב וכן שמאל, Vechen yoshev vechen smol,
similarly one who sits and the left hand." So now here the
focus is not left hand, the focus is זר, zar a non-כהן
Kohen cannot do the הולכה. holacha So how could you claim that
he could be good? So of course the question is, רב ששת,
Rav Sheshet, if you knew this ברייתא, braita why did you bother
asking the question? But maybe he knew that either רב חסדא Rav
Chisda or רב חסדא's Rav Chisda אמורא Amora was teaching otherwise, and
therefore he wanted to set him straight. So he said, "How could
you be saying a זר zar can do the הולכה holacha based
on this פסוק pasuk if we have a ברייתא braita that says
a זר zar cannot do the הולכה?" holacha So one minute, we'll
finish that story in a minute, but for our immediate question, look.
רב ששת Rav Sheshet knew this ברייתא braita that says that a
זר zar cannot do the הולכה, holacha and the same ברייתא braita
says that you cannot do the הולכה holacha with the left hand.
So how yesterday did רב ששת Rav Sheshet say you could do
the הולכה holacha with the left hand based on what you did
by the קטורת? ketoret Here's a ברייתא braita, that he clearly knows
that says you can't do the הולכה holacha. with the left hand.
So what's the answer? הגמרא Hagemara says, it's
what's the order of which these things happened? בתר דשמעה הדר ביה.
Batar deshama hadar beih. Okay, after he heard this ברייתא, braita meaning
the order was: first he thought that you could do הולכה holacha
with the left hand, he was challenged by a ברייתא braita. that
says you could not do the הולכה holacha with the left hand.
So then he learned that ברייתא. braita Now he learns that there's
a ברייתא braita, out there that says you can't do הולכה holacha
with the left and a זר zar. can't do הולכה. holacha Now
that he knows that ברייתא, braita he used at a later stage,
he used that ברייתא braita to challenge רב חסדא's Rav Chisda אמורא
Amora who said you could do הולכה holacha with a non-כהן. Kohen
And that's the order of this. So what have we concluded here?
We concluded that yesterday רב ששת Rav Sheshet said you could do
the הולכה holacha with the left based on the קטורת. ketores. But
today began by saying a ברייתא braita? explicitly said הולכה holacha could
not be done with the left, and therefore הגמרא Hagemara says fine,
רב ששת Rav Sheshet was wrong, we reject that idea, you cannot
do הולכה holacha with the left hand. How did רב ששת Rav
Sheshet make that mistake? Doesn't רב ששת Rav Sheshet know this ברייתא?
braita Because the same ברייתא braita says no הולכה holacha with the
left also says no הולכה holacha, with a non-כהן, Kohen and רב
ששת Rav Sheshet knew that ברייתא braita and used that ברייתא braita,
to challenge רב חסדא's Rav Chisda אמורא. Amora. So the answer is
yes, once he himself was challenged with that ברייתא, braita he now
knows that ברייתא braita. and is able to turn around and challenge
somebody else. And the conclusion is, although הולכה holacha in theory is
not as significant, it's just getting it there and it could sometimes
be done without, nevertheless when you are doing it, it's invalid whether
it's left hand and invalid whether it is a non-כהן. Kohen And
one second, Dov has a question and then we'll get to Michael,
but before that, the question should be: Okay, so I get it,
you got a ברייתא. braita But what about the argument we made
yesterday? What about the argument that if you could do the קטורת
ketoret הולכה with the left, you should be able to do the
הולכה of the blood with the left? You're still doing the קטורת
ketoret with the left. Why is that different? So this goes by—this
goes to the point I've been telling you all along, and this
is pointed out very briefly in the תוספות ישנים. Tosafot Yeshanim So
if you take a look at the תוספות Tosafot ישנים here on
the bottom of the page here, with the first line in the
middle, וכן שמאל קשיא, Vechen smol kashya, ומתניתין אין ראיה, umatnitin ein
reaya, how about the fact that you would do it by the
קטורת? ketoret That's different, משום דלא אפשר. mishum dela efshar. There's no
alternative because you have to have one thing in your right and
one thing in your left, you need two hands. And I would
also say because if the מלא חפניו mlo chofnav involves the left,
so you see already the left hand is being validated for some
of these things by the קטורת. ketoret. דקרינן
ליה נמי בגמרא רבה הוכשר בו ביום הכפורים, Dekarinan leh nami begemara
rabba huchshar bo beyom hakippurim, and in another גמרא, gemara it says
that the left hand was a special exception by יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. So fine. Now... Of course you could have said not only
was it at לא אפשר, lo efshar, but you could have said
going back to the larger theme that these things of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur do not exactly parallel the עבודות you would do by
the דם, dam, as we said yesterday and the beginning of today.
The חפינה chafina is not exactly the same as the שחיטה. shechita
The putting in of vessel is not exactly the same as the
casting of the blood. So maybe the הלכה halacha is also not
the same. But anyway, so there are two points of possible
difference here.
But we were questioning it. In one way we said it is
parallel, you could have a סברת פיגול. s'varat pigul. In one way
we said maybe not, maybe if you spill it it is not
a problem. So I am just saying there are two questions to
raise here. One is the ongoing theme of to what degree are
these things done by the חפינה chafina exactly the same types of
things that were done by the blood with the same laws? And
the other issue is even if as a general rule they are,
which is still debated, then maybe there is nevertheless going to be
an exception because here you had to use the left hand, you
did not have an alternative. טוב, tov, you had a question.
I want to know if you have anything to say about the
structure of the ברייתא braita independent of the way in which it
is being used here. What I mean is זר ואונן שיכור ובעל
מום בקבלה והולכה וזריקה פסול. zar v'onen shikur u'ba'al mum b'kabala v'holacha
v'zrika pasul. Okay, good. וכן
יושב, v'chen yoshev, and
I know it is not totally unusual, but why it is like
a appendix, it is like a...
Well, I would say first of all the first four things are
basically statuses of the person. Meaning what you are בגברא be-gavra as
opposed to the next part which is, which is you are okay
as a person allowed to do the עבודה, Avoda but the way
you're doing the עבודה is incorrect. Right, just also going back to
the whole issue of an oral tradition, thank you, sometimes the way
things are easy to memorize. זר ואונן שיכור בעל מום בקבלה ובהולכה
ובזריקה, zar v'onen shikur ba'al mum b'kabala u'v'holacha u'v'zrika, right, בקבלה ובהולכה
ובזריקה, b'kabala u'v'holacha u'v'zrika, like it's like a four and a three,
there's a certain rhythm as opposed to if you made a list
of six and then three it would have lost sense.
So really that structure reveals a lot about the poetic
nature of the way in which these traditions...
Right, but there also is a logic to that categorizing. Yeah.
My question is so can we infer from that that let's say,
okay, so זר zar wants to go מטיב את המנורה, mative et
hamenorah, that's okay, I mean like... Why? Because only those three it's
פסול.
Well, first of all possibly you might have remembered that there was
a גמרא Gemara. we did much before that said that הדלקת נרות
hadlakas neiros isn't an עבודה and actually did raise the question about
a זר. zar.
Right, so this is, I
don't know, that's always a question.
What about when he מעלה איברים ma'ala evarim on הכבש? hakevesh?
Well, that's also the issue of וכי זר קרב אל
המזבח? v'chi zar kareiv el hamizbeach? But again, also there's a different
question about whether you're allowed to and whether it would invalidate. So
this is just saying what things invalidate, that's a different question about
what would be allowed or not allowed. Okay, alright, I don't know,
so you have to ask
if he can even be in the מזבח, mizbeach, in the עזרה,
azara, in
certain environments yes, certain no. Anyway, look, you have to look at
each thing individually. You're right. You can't assume the whole story. You
do have to explore those other issues. So now let's get back
to the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara. says like this. Okay,
so that's why now we know a זר zar. and use of
the left hand cannot be good by הולכה, whatever happens by the
קטורת ketoret? with הולכה is a special exception. But now we've got
an issue. You quoted a ברייתא braita but what about the פסוק?
pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says ורב חסדא קרא קאמר. v'rav chisda
kra ka'amar. So now the גמרא Gemara assumes that when the אמורא
amora said it back he actually checked with Rav Chisda that this
was Rav Chisda's initial position, that you could use your left hand,
excuse me, that you could do it with a זר. zar So
it's very nice you have a ברייתא braita but Rav Chisda had
this פסוק pasuk in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim that said that the
כהנים kohanim were throwing from the hands of the זר. zar So
it sounds like the זר zar did the carrying. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, דאביד מעשה אצטבא. d'avid maise itztaba. He was just
acting as a pedestal. What does that mean? It means the זר
zar was holding the vessel and the כהן Kohen was taking it
from the hands and doing the זריקה, zrika, but it doesn't mean
the זר zar, conveyed it. It means the זר zar checked it,
the כהן Kohen caught the blood, the כהן Kohen conveyed it, handed
it to the זר, zar the זר zar, just put out his
hand like this and just basically acted completely as a pedestal without
doing as if you would an act. He's completely passive, right, and
therefore it's not like the זר zar did an act and an
עבודה, he just was placed on the זר, the זר was almost
inanimate in the way he was functioning.
Okay, this by the way interestingly comes up in a number of
ראשונים rishonim in the first משנה mishna in שבת, Shabbos, where people
remember the first משנה mishna it talks about the poor person standing
out in the street and the owner in the house and handing
the bread out to the poor person, and when are they both
doing an act of carrying or only one of them is doing
it? And one case is like the owner takes the bread or
let's say the poor person takes the bread from the hands of
the owner. And in that case, the poor person did the entire
מלאכה, melacha, he took from inside the house and brought it out.
But the question the ראשונים rishonim ask is that the גמרא Gemara
makes it sound like the owner did nothing wrong. So the ראשונים
rishonim say why did the owner do nothing wrong? Why isn't that
like לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, why isn't he at least being a
מסייע? m'sayeiah? He's at least participating in it? And they basically use
this phrase: No. It's מעשה אצטבא. maaseh istaba. He is completely just
being completely passive, not actually doing any action. He's acting like an
inanimate object, and in that case, you can't sort of attach any
blame to him. Of course, you could've said he could've stopped it,
but okay. Let's back to the
גמרא.
Gemara בעי רב פפא. Ba'i Rav Pappa. Yes. Different loads. In
case of שבת Shabbos where we're investigating the parameters
of a מלאכה. melacha. Right. We worked that out. But here it
seems like
we're...
Well, the difference is there it's a question of fault in what
was done and you could have at least
intervened, right?
Whereas here, it stretches credulity that this is really what, you know,
what the תורה Torah had in mind where it says participates or
whatever was the תורה Torah דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, but okay, right.
Right, I mean, that's always the practice of stretching פסוקים to make
them work.
Yeah, I gotta tell you this is really short. Like I spent
a long time teaching that משנה Mishna to the eighth graders. I
got stuck, no no, I got stuck on this one moment and
there was a girl in the group and the guys were all
contending like, he just stood there, he didn't do anything, he just
stood there. So the girl went like this, she said, "He put
something in the guy's hand. Okay, hold that thing. Now I'm gonna
take it from you." So she takes the thing and the guy
goes like that. She says, "You see? You cannot be stationary. It's
not possible, you have to move even a little bit." They went
crazy. The guys went crazy and she stood her ground. It was
like a magnificent moment. That's great.
That's great.
Very cool.
What do you mean passive? A human being can't be completely passive.
Right, right.
She's got it. That's great. Okay. So now בעי רב פפא. Ba'i
Rav Pappa. We see that רב פפא Rav Pappa has a whole
list of questions about the חפינה chafina and what are its parameters.
So let's take a new
one. בעי רב פפא. Ba'i Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa asked
חפן חבירו ונתן לתוך חפניו מהו? chafan chaveiro venasan le-toch chofnav mahu?
So remember we asked the other day whether you needed to do
the חפינה chafina, or could you do it with a כלי. kli.
But presumably you needed to do the act of חפינה. chafina? So
now he says, does it have to be the same person? Let's
say one person does the חפינה chafina, and puts it into the
hands of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So maybe it has to
be the same person? Do you need a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
to do the חפינה? chafina. Maybe somebody else could do the חפינה?
chafina... Because remember it says ולקח מלא המחתה velakach melo hamachta or
it says ולקח גחלי אש velakach gachalei esh ומלא חפניו, umelo chofnav,
he will take מלא חפניו, melo chofnav, but it doesn't say that
he does the חפינה. chafina, So he just takes מלא חפניו. melo
chofnav. So somebody else does the חפינה chafina even if you need
it to do the act of חפינה chafina as long as the
other person has bigger hands it's not a problem, then it'll fill
up his hands. So maybe somebody else does the חפינה chafina, and
pours it into his hands? So okay, מהו מלא חפניו בעינן ואיכא?
mahu melo chofnav ba'inan ve-ika? Now his hands are full and an
act of it was done with hands as opposed to before when
we asked about doing it with a vessel. או דלמא ולקח והביא
בעינן? o dilma velakach ve-heivi ba'inan? The act ולקח velakach goes on
the מלא חפניו melo chofnav as well and he has to do
the act himself of the taking. A, it has to either be
the same person that does the ולקח lakach and the והביא, heivi,
or B, at least it has to be a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. So let's take a look. וליכא תיקו. uleka teiku. So we
don't know the answer. Now the difference between whether it's a question
of the same person or whether it's a question of needing a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would be the following scenario which the גמרא
Gemara is going to get to. A כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does
it and then drops dead
before another כהן גדול Kohen Gadol comes and takes it out of
the dead כהן's Kohen hand. Out of my dead hands! Try it
anyway. So then it was done by a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
but it wasn't done by the same כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. What
would be the story? So anyway here it seems like the issue
is not כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, it's the issue of the same
person. So let's just take a little bit more in the גמרא.
Gemara בעי רבי יהושע בן לוי. Ba'i Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. So
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi asked:
חפן ומת. chafan umet. Now in this case he did the חפינה,
chafina the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and then he died. מה שיכנס
אחר בחפינתו? mah she-yikanes acher be-chafinato? Can another person use his חפינה?
chafina So again it's not the same person. There's a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol both stages but it's not the same. What's the story?
Just like the previous question. אמר רבי חנינה. Amar Rabbi Chanina. So
said רבי חנינה: Rabbi Chanina: בוא וראה שאלת הראשונים. bo u-re'ei she'elas
harishonim. Look at the question that the earlier ones asked me, meaning
presumably רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi was an older...
of the earlier generation and he basically was saying, "Look, you know,
we were asking similar questions and here it was even asked by
the earlier generation by רבי יהושע בן לוי." Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
So before the גמרא Gemara gets to the answer it has a
whole digression who was older here. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says... So now we're on...
Wait, wasn't there a טומאה tumah
problem?
Yeah, no, right, you're right.
Okay, okay, you are absolutely right. I was making it too graphic.
He has to have taken the חפינה, chafina put it into the
כף, kaf, and then dropped dead.
Oh, he must have...
Okay, sorry about that. Okay, so that's what he had to do.
Right, he did not take it out of his dead hands. Fine.
He
did the חפינה. chafina In one scenario, if it wasn't dropping dead,
one כהן kohein could do the חפינה... chafina, pour it into the
כהן גדול'ס Kohen Gadol's hands. But in this case, where the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol at both stages, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does
it, pours it into the כף, kaf, drops dead, and the next
one takes it out of the כף. kaf. Wait, wait. Let's read,
let us, shh, let's get a little further, then you can have
your questions. Okay. So, אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says first of all, למימרא דרבי יהושע בן לוי
קשיש? L'maimra d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi Kashish? This suggests since he said,
oh wow, look at this great question even the, you know, the
older generation asked, the first generation asked, it sounds like רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is older. ואמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי, V'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, ברבי יהושע בן לוי b'Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi said, התיר לי רבי חנינא, hitir li Rabbi Chanina, so
now רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi we think is
the older of the two, said רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina who we
think is the younger of the two, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina allowed
me לשתות שחליים בשבת, lishtot shachlayim b'shabbat, to drink שחליים shachlayim on
שבת. Shabbat. Now, what is שחליים? shachlayim?
What's your English translate? Something like cress or some, what is it?
Cress juice, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says, so now before we
answer this question that the fact that he said רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina allowed me suggests that רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina is the older
authority, the more author, you know, the the greater one, we have
now we're going to digress about the question about cress juice on
שבת. Shabbat. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לשתות, lishtot, פשיטא, pshita, just to drink it, of course you can
drink it. תנן, Tnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, כל האוכלים
אוכל אדם לרפואה, kol ha'ochlim ochel adam l'refuah, anything that is a
food, you can eat even though your purpose of eating it is
for is for medicinal or health purposes. There's an issue of taking
something that's clearly a medicine, but something that's a food and you're
eating it because it's it's important for your health, so that's fine.
וכל המשקין שותה אדם, V'chol hamashkin shoteh adam, and a person can
drink anything for רפואה refuah purposes if it's basically not a medicine.
So presumably if healthy people would drink cress juice, of course you
can drink it. אלא, Ella, no, the question is not "can I
drink it," the question was לשחוק ולשתות, lishchok v'lishtot, can I grind
it and drink it, שחליים בשבת, shachlayim b'shabbat, can you do that?
So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the scenario?
אי דאיכא סכנה, Ee d'ika sakana, if there's some type of a
life danger, מישרא שרי, mishra shari, of course it's allowed. ואי דליכא
סכנה, Ve'ee d'leka sakana, if there's no life danger, מיסר אסיר, missar
asir, of course it's forbidden. We're not going into הלכות שבת hilchot
Shabbat exactly what's the איסור issur of grinding, but whatever, טוחן tochen
something, okay, of course it's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
לעולם דאיכא סכנה, le'olam d'ika sakana, there is a danger. הכי קמיבעיא
ליה, Hachi kamiba'ei lei, this was his question. מי מסיא, Mi masya,
is this thing really helpful? Does this is really just a בבא
מעשה bubbe meise or does cress juice really provide healing דנחלל עליה
שבת, d'nechalel aleih Shabbat, that we could be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat
in order to make it? או לא מסיא, O lo masya, maybe
it really does not, you know, is of no medicinal value, ולא
נחלל עליה שבת, v'lo nechalel aleih Shabbat, and we cannot be מחלל
שבת. mechallel Shabbat. And then he says רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina allowed
me. Now, the גמרא gemara says, ומשנה רבי חנינא, u'mashna Rabbi Chanina,
so why did he go to רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina to ask
this question? משום דבקי ברפואות, Mishum d'baki b'refuot,
because רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina knew medicine. How do we know רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina knew medicine? This is like one digression after another.
דאמר רבי חנינא, D'amar Rabbi Chanina, because רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said,
מעולם לא שאלני אדם על מכת פרדה לבנה וחיה, mei'olam lo she'alani
adam al makat pirdah levana v'chayah, nobody ever asked me about being
bitten by, smitten literally but bitten by, a white mule and survived.
So people are asking him medical questions and he said I was
never שאל, she'al, you know, I never had a patient come to
me who had been bitten by a white mule and survived. Obviously
he gets a lot of people coming to him, he's a doctor,
he knows medicine. Story of his life.
What? He's flirting with you.
Well, now the גמרא gemara now asks that. Think about all the
digressions. Was he really older? I'm going to show you this whole
discussion. One minute, how what's the question about שבת? Shabbat? Okay, and
why do you ask him because he's a doctor? Wait a minute,
is that really true about the thing about the white mule? והא
קחזינן דחיה, V'ha kachazinan d'chayah, we actually see that people actually do
survive after being bitten by a white mule. No, אימא וחיית, eima
v'chayat, no, it means that the that the wound never fully healed,
the person might have survived but the wound didn't heal. והא קחזינן
דמיתסי, V'ha kachazinan d'mitzi,
but we do see those wounds heal. Okay, בסומקן אינהו וחיורן ריש
כרעיהו
קמי, b'sumkan inu v'chivan reish kara'aihu kami, no, the cases we're talking
about about the particularly infectious wounds or whatever, unhealing wounds is when
the is when the mule is actually a red but it has
white legs. Anyway, now
that we've figured out the question about cress juice and now that
we've figured out about the evidence that he was a doctor and
what the story is with white mules, we're back to the issue
that you see that רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was the elder. Now,
how do you see that? After we've done this wonderful demonstration that
the reason he asked רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was because רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina was a doctor, he wasn't asking him because he was
the wiser sage, he wanted to know in order to פסקן paskin
a שבת שאלה, Shabbat sha'alah, he had to have the right medical
information, so he asked the doctor.
How do we prove he was younger?
Sorry, so how do you see that he was older? So רש"י
Rashi says, you know the whole evidence that he was older was
that he used the word רבי. Rabbi. Because if רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina had been younger, of course you would have asked him, he's
the doctor, but we said מכאן התיר לי
חנינא, mikan hitir li Chanina, not רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. So the
use of the word רבי, Rabbi, רש"י says. Yes.
He just says an example that the example is that nobody ever,
he didn't heal anybody.
What?
He didn't heal anybody.
Right, no, no, but the point is
The point was
was that the only people that people go to ask about medical
conditions are doctors. I know, yeah, it is a little funny. Okay,
so מכל מקום, mikol makom, okay, שמע
מינא. shma mina. מכל מקום שמע מינא דרבי חנינא קשיש. mikol makom
shma mina d'Rebbi Chanina kashish. You see Rebbi Chanina was the elder
one. So what is Rebbi Chanina saying? Oh, look this great question
of of the earlier generation. What do you mean the earlier generation?
He's the older one! אלא הכי קאמר. ela hachi ka'amar. So this
is what he means. When Rebbi Yehoshua, who was Rebbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, asked this question, not that it was the question of an
earlier generation, here's what he's saying. שאלתנו, shaltanu, you, Rebbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, have asked us
כשאלה של ראשונים, k'sheila shel rishonim, the type of questions that the
earlier generation had asked. Meaning not that Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi was
the earlier generation. When Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi asked the question, Rebbi
Chanina said to him that generation, question that you're asking has been
asked already in the earlier generation. Fine, so that solves that whole
question of who was earlier. Back to the point that Rebbi Yehoshua
ben Levi was asking about one כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does חפינה,
chafina, then he dies as was pointed out, it was put into
the into the ladle. Can the other כהן גדול Kohen Gadol finish
with חפינה chafina of the first one? Does the one same person
have to do the חפינה chafina that is taking it inside? So
let's see what the answer is. I'll take—I know some people have
some questions, but I want to get to the answer and then
we go back. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומי אמר
רבי חנינא הכי? u'mi amar Rebbi Chanina hachi? Now, again, we're not
even—we're still avoiding getting to the answer. How could Rebbi Chanina have
thought that this was a legitimate question? Why would it not have
been a legitimate question? ואמר רבי חנינא, v'amar Rebbi Chanina, because Rebbi
Chanina said בפר ולא בדמו של פר. b'par v'lo b'damo shel par.
The פסוק pasuk says בזאת יבא אהרן אל הקדש בפר בן בקר
לחטאת. bezos yavo Aharon el hakodesh b'par ben bakar l'chatas. With the
cow. And he's not actually going into the sanctuary with the cow;
he's going with the blood of the cow. So why does the
תורה Torah refer to it as בפר? b'par?
So what Rebbi Chanina says is that בפר b'par means that the
blood of the cow he has to have taken from the cow
itself. Can't be somebody else took the blood from the cow. What
does that mean? כהן גדול Kohen Gadol number one—I mean the only
one at the time—שוחט shocht the cow and the blood is caught.
Then he drops dead. Enter in כהן גדול Kohen Gadol number two.
Can he pick up where כהן גדול Kohen Gadol number one left
off? Can he start with the blood of the cow? Or does
he have to start with the cow itself? That's the question. According
to the דרשה drasha that says בפר ואפילו בדמו של פר, b'par
v'afilu b'damo shel par, he can pick up where the first guy
left off. According to Rebbi Chanina who says בפר ולא בדמו של
פר, b'par v'lo b'damo shel par, no, you gotta start with the
cow, you gotta go back all the way to the beginning and
שוחט shocht the cow and do it all again. Now, consider now
what our scenario is because that is our scenario, right? Remember what
happened. We
had
פר par and וידוי vidui number one, okay? Then we had the
שעירים, se'irim, right? With the גורלות, goralos, okay? Right? Then we had
פר par and וידוי vidui number two, right? Then we had the
שחיטה, shechitah, the קבלה, kabala, right? Somebody is stirring it, right? Then
we had the גחלים gechalim from the מזבח, mizbeach, then we had
the חפינה, chafina, and that's sort of where we're up to. And
then into the כף. kaf. Okay, that's sort of where we're up
to, right? And our question is this guy does the חפינה chafina.
and drops dead. Can another כהן Kohen. pick up here with the—and
do the—and take the חפינה chafina and continue? Okay, but what happened?
You have the blood of the פר par and you are also
going to have another כהן picking up with the blood of the
פר. par. The blood hasn't been thrown yet.
The חפינה chafina is parallel to the שחיטה?
Not parallel, no parallel! If the כהן drops dead here, not only
does he have to pick up to do the קטרת, ketores, you're
going to have to finish the blood of the פר par because
it hasn't been thrown yet. Ah, okay. So if you say בפר
ולא בדמו של פר, b'par v'lo b'damo shel par, once the כהן
drops dead, you're going to have to go all the way back
here, right? And if you go back here, you're going to have
to do everything again. So you have to do it in order.
It's linked. You have to do everything in order is the assumption.
What about בעדו? ba'ado? If it says בפר שיכפר בעדו, b'par sheyekaper
ba'ado, so if somebody is taking some—the פר par that another כהן
did, it's not בעדו ba'ado anymore!
All right, so that could be part of the argument. Okay, so
you're saying—you're focusing on the וידוי. vidui. As we pointed out before,
the וידוי vidui is a very heightened focus for us. For the
in the question about the עבודה it was not; there was opinions
that the וידוי vidui isn't מעכב. me'akev. All right? All right, but
then this is opposite. Anyway, so the point is is that how
can you ask whether you could continue with the חפינה chafina if
you're of the Rebbi Chanina position? If you're Rebbi Chanina, you gotta
go all the way back to the beginning! So it's not even
a question, it's a moot point. So let's take a look. So
the
גמרא Gemara says: ומי אמר רבי חנינא הכי ואמר רבי חנינא בפר
ולא בדמו של פר? u'mi amar Rebbi Chanina hachi v'amar Rebbi Chanina
b'par v'lo b'damo shel par? ואמר רבי חנינא קטורת שחפנה קודם שחיטת
הפר. v'amar Rebbi Chanina ketores shechafna kodem shechitas hapar. Now, maybe you'll
say, "Oh, but you know it doesn't matter if you do the
order different, maybe you can do the שחיטה after the קטורת." ketoret
No, we know he says also that the order matters, that if
you did the קטורת ketores, before you שחט shechted the פר, par,
לא עשה ולא כלום, lo asah velo klum, it's invalid. So since
he says you have to go all the way back and שחט
shecht the פר par again, and he says you can't do the
קטורת before the פר, par, you'd have to do the קטורת again.
So it's a moot question. Of course you gotta do it again
because you gotta go all the way back to the beginning. So
the גמרא Gemara says: No, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is the
question: וממילא
קמיבעיא ליה הא, u'mimeila kamibaya lei ha, what רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
is saying to רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is
the following: since you're asking this question of the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol dropping dead after the חפינה, chafina so מכלל דקסבר בפר ואפילו
בדמו של פר, mikhla dekasvar bepar ve'afilu bedamo shel par, you obviously,
you רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi who asked the
question are obviously assuming that you don't have to go back to
do the שחיטה. You could continue with the blood. And since you
could continue with the blood, you want to know what the story
is with the קטורת. ומאי דסבירא ליה, umai desevira lei, according to
your assumptions that you can continue from that point on with the
blood, שאילתו כשאלת הראשונים, she'ilato kish'elat harishonim, your question was like the
question that earlier ones asked. Meaning: me personally, I think this is
a moot question. As soon as you drop dead, the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol drops dead, you gotta go back to the beginning. But
for you, that you think that you could continue with the blood,
then that question you asked is a good question: can you also
continue with the קטורת? It's like the earlier question. Now, the earlier
question nobody was dropping dead, so you didn't have this problem. The
earlier question was just one person comes and does the חפינה, chafina,
maybe a non-כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and pours it into the hand
of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Your question about the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol dropping dead is very similar. Of course, it only makes
sense if you can continue here and you don't have to worry
about going back and doing the פר par again. But assuming the
blood isn't the problem, your question of dropping dead is similar to
that other question: can one כהן continue with a חפינה chafina done
by somebody else?
Yeah, I don't see how it's different than the first question.
Well, the only difference is is that you might say it doesn't
have to be the same person, but it has to be a
כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Right, I said that's what I thought for everything.
So how is it different than everything? No! As we said before,
there are certain things that don't need a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
like the drawing of the lots doesn't need a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, the שחיטה of the פר par might not need a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. One of the themes all along is which of
the components are not considered עבודה per se that might not need
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the first question raised the issue
of, which we've been dealing with all of yesterday, is חפינה chafina
an עבודה? Right? Can you have a מחשבת פיגול machshevet pigul or
something? So that would raise the question: could it be a non-כהן
גדול? Kohen Gadol? Here, this question is a little sharper: let's even
assume it is a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, can it be a
different person? What if he drops dead? Now, that's only you're only
able to ask it assuming in terms of the blood, you don't
have to go back to the beginning. But assuming you don't have
to go back, now we focus on this issue: forget the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, it's כהן גדול Kohen Gadol both parts, but does
it have to be the same person? Okay, so now we've got
to the question. Let's see what the answer is. Let's take a
look. So מאי הוי עלה? mai hava ala? So you have a
whole long discussion of who was older and doctors and the blood
and all that, but okay, what about this question? Can... does it
have to be the same person? What was the conclusion? So אמר
רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, says רב פפא: Rav Pappa: אי חופן
וחוזר וחופן, ei chofen vechozer vechofen, if you, the person who once
you've done the חפינה, chafina. you do it a second time in
the קדשי קדשים, Kodeshei Kodashim, חברו נכנס בחפינתו, chavero nichnas bechafinato, then
somebody else can use the previous כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol's חפינה. chafina,
Why? דקא מקיים חפינה, deka mekayem chafina, because you'll wind up doing
the חפינה chafina, anyway. Meaning: we have been focusing, hyper-focusing, on the
חפינה chafina that's done, you know,
in preparation, outside the היכל, Heichal, you know, scooping it up, putting
it into the, what do you call it? Putting it into the
ladle. What happens when you get into the קדשי קדשים? Kodeshei Kodashim?
So, as I mean, if people have learned this before, and we're
going to quote a ברייתא braita in a minute that's going to
be very clear, you pour the ladle back into your hands and
you do another חפינה chafina. and then you release it. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara now is considering that that might not be the
case. Maybe you take it straight from the ladle—this would make your
life a lot easier—and just pour it straight over over the fire.
You don't put it back in your hands. You did the חפינה
chafina, earlier, it's מלא חפניו, melo chofnav, you have the חפינה, chafina.
and now you're pouring it. You're pouring it through a vessel. Who
needs to pour it from your hand? So this is the question
whether חופן וחוזר וחופן. chofen vechozer vechofen. You did the חפינה chafina.
on the outside, do you have to do it again on the
inside or can you go straight from the vessel? So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: let's take a look. If you say,
let's read it again: אי חופן וחוזר וחופן, ei chofen vechozer vechofen,
if you have to do it again in the קדשי קדשים, Kodeshei
Kodashim, then חברו נכנס בחפינתו, chavero nichnas bechafinato, you can, the second
guy can use the חפינה chafina of the first dead guy. Why?
דקא מקיים חפינה, deka mekayem chafina, because the second guy will also
do a חפינה. chafina. So we're assuming you need to do a
חפינה, chafina. and the same כהן has to do the חפינה, chafina.
but maybe any חפינה chafina works. It doesn't have to be the
one outside, maybe the one on the inside will be the one
that counts. And that'll be fine. אי אין חופן וחוזר וחופן, ei
ein chofen vechozer vechofen, if you don't do it a second time,
you pour it straight from the ladle, then תיבעי לך, tiba'ei lach,
that's a good question because then you personally are not doing your
own חפינה. chafina Somebody else did it for... somebody else did it:
the dead כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. And then that's the question about:
can you use one if you are not going to... If you're
going to do it again, of course you could do it.
If you're not the one who did a חפינה, chafina. right, can
you then pick up and complete?
Exactly. Exactly. So that's what he thinks the answer is. So אמר
ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא, amar leh Rav Huna
brei d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rav Papa, so Rav Huna said back to Rav
Papa, אדרבה, aderaba, I would have said the exact opposite based on
this question. אי חופן וחוזר וחופן, ee chofen v'chozer v'chofen, if you
did it on the outside, you have to go ahead and do
it back again on the inside, לא יכנס אחר בחפינתו. lo yikanes
acher b'chafinato. You can't use the other guy's. Why not? אי אפשר,
ee efshar,
Michael here, you should be very happy, שלא יחסר ושלא יותיר. shelo
yechsar v'shelo yotir. It's impossible it will be the exact same size
of the חפינה. chafina. So even if there's more, right, and you
get everything into your hands, but it's not the same חפינה. chafina?
So if both things are part of the עבודה, then how can
then they have to be the same. This מלא חפניו m'lo chofnav
is not the same as this. That חפינה chafina, is not the
same as this חפינה. chafina Shouldn't be good. ואין חופן חוזר וחופן,
v'ein chofen chozer v'chofen, however, if you don't have to do it
again, תיבעי לך, tiba'ei lakh, then it's a legitimate question. I don't
have to make it my חפינה. chafina It would be the dead
guy's חפינה. chafina Fine, but it was his חפינה chafina and it's
still a מלא חפניו m'lo chofnav of his מלא חפניו. m'lo chofnav.
Then we could raise the issue. Okay, it's still a little bit
funny because I am now putting on the, pouring the incense, and
it's not my מלא חפניו. m'lo chofnav. It was a different person's
מלא חפניו, m'lo chofnav, but that's the question. Can you stitch the
two halves together? When it was taken, it was the מלא חפניו
m'lo chofnav of the כהן גדול. kohein gadol. Now I'm a different
כהן גדול, kohein gadol, but I could still maybe use his. Okay,
so if you're using the old thing, it's a little funny, it's
not yours, but that's the
question. Does it have to be yours? Maybe it could be what
somebody else did. Okay, but if it's חופן וחוזר וחופן, chofen v'chozer
v'chofen, then there has to be a continuity. It has to be
the same חפינה chafina and they have to match. So that's what
he says. He says, I would have said the exact opposite in
terms of which way is more obvious.
Okay. Does the עבודה of מלא חפניו m'lo chofnav lend meaning to
the קטורת or lend meaning to the human being who's doing the
action?
Okay, that's an interesting way of thinking about it. Not sure I
agree, but I hear the point. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
and now we don't have an answer. So we don't know about
חופן וחוזר וחופן. chofen v'chozer v'chofen. That's left as an unanswered question.
And now we move into this question about do you have to
do another
חפינה. Khafina What's an unanswered question, excuse me, is whether you can
use another person's חפינה. Khafina Whether the other person is a כהן
גדול kohein gadol or not a כהן גדול, kohein gadol, can another
person do the initial חפינה? Khafina But now, we don't answer that
and we move into חופן וחוזר וחופן. chofen v'chozer v'chofen. Okay, תיבעי
להו, tiba'ei lehu, that question was raised. חופן חוזר וחופן או לא?
chofen chozer v'chofen o lo? If you do the first חפינה, Khafina
once you do the first חפינה Khafina do you have to do
another one or not? So תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear,
and you might recognize this because this is exactly what we said
a few דפים dappim ago. We tried to prove it from the
משנה. mishna. כך היתה מידתה. kakh hay'ta midata. It speaks about taking
the חפינה Khafina and then after it says about the big one
and the small כהן according to their size of their hand, this
was its measure. What's the point of those extra three words, this
was its measure? So מאי לאו, mai lav, what this must mean
is, כשם שמידתו מבחוץ כך מידתו מבפנים. keshem she-midato mibachutz kakh midato
mibifnim. It must mean that the same way you did the measuring
and the חפינה Khafina on the outside of the היכל, heichal, you
did it again on the inside. Those extra words mean you did
another חפינה Khafina once you got into the קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim.
Gmara says, לא, lo, no, that's not necessarily what it means. דילמא,
dilma, maybe what that phrase means is, שמא רצה לעשות מידה עושה.
shema ratza la'asot mida oseh. We raised that question, maybe you don't
have to do the חפינה with your hands. Maybe you can scoop
it out with a pre-measured vessel. Maybe you don't have to use
your hands in the scooping. אי נמי, ee nami, or maybe what
that phrase means is שלא יחסר ולא יותיר. shelo yechsar v'lo yotir.
That it has to be precisely that size, cannot be any bit
over, any bit under. So that phrase can mean a lot of
things. Okay, so let's try again. תא שמע, ta shma, come and
hear. And again we get flanked by a large תוספות. תא שמע
כיצד הוא עושה. ta shma keitzad hu oseh. This is a very
explicit ברייתא of what you do when you're in the קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. What do you do? אוחז את הבזך. ocheiz et habazikh.
Now the כף, kaf, what was called the כף, kaf, the ladle,
is now called the בזך, bazikh, but it's similar, some type of
a long vessel with a long arm that is containing the incense.
So you hold it בראש אצבעותיו, b'rosh etzbe'otav, either using the tips
of your fingers. ויש אומרים בשיניו, v'yeish omrim b'shinav, some say your
teeth. Again, it's quite funny because the גמרא Gemara before spoke about
how the use of your teeth is inappropriate, but תוספות said, okay,
but sometimes you gotta do it, you don't have
alternatives. ומעלה בגודלו, u-ma'aleh b'godlo, and you pull it up until your
thumbs, or with your thumbs, עד שמגיע לבין אצילי ידיו, ad she-magia
l'vein atzilei yadav, until it becomes, gets to between your elbows. Which
basically means, what does it mean? It means, I should have brought
a, I should have brought an example. But let's say... what? Joy.
Yeah, I don't know about joy here. Let's say this is the
arm of the... I've got a ladle, this is the arm and
there's the head of the ladle. So I'm having this in this
hand, okay, I put down my the coals. Now I've got, I
could pour it all into one hand, but I've got to pour
it into two hands. How do I pour it into two hands?
So what I do is I like use my... my fingers and
my thumbs or whatever to move it so that now it's sort
of being held like this. Okay, held underneath my arm. And now
I use, if it's got a long arm and the head of
it, the spoon part of it, reaches from under my arm to
where my hands are, right? So then I can somehow twist it,
I don't know exactly how, because I'm not exactly sure how I'm
going to do it.
Not all over the place.
That I know I'm going to do it. Okay. Anyway, somehow I
do it. Okay. וחוזר ומחזירה לתוך חפניו V'chozer Machazira L'toch Chofnav
and somehow using your underarms or your elbows or your teeth, you
get it all into your
hands. וצברה V'tzavra and
then you mound it up, you put it in a mound on
the coals, כדי שתהא עשנה שוהה לבוא. K'dei She'ashana Shohe Lavoh.
So first, the first opinion is you put the whole thing as
one unit as a mound on, so it takes time for the
smoke to arrive. Time maybe for you to leave before the smoke
arrives up. ויש אומרים V'yesh Omrim and some say מפיזרה, Mifazre, no,
you scatter it on the coals, כדי שתהא עשנה ממהרת לבוא, K'dei
She'ashana Miaheret Lavoh, so the smoke should rise up very quickly. That's
already a very fascinating question, right? To the degree that the burning
of the incense to some degree evokes or allows for the sense
of this encounter with God, it's very much like the interesting question
Rabbi Dov in the ישיבה Yeshiva on the last day was talking
about the debate in the מדרש Midrash about whether Moshe did the
right thing or the wrong thing by averting his gaze, you know,
at the burning bush. So here you are, you're finally there in
the קדשי קדשים Kodesh Kodashim in the most intimate moment, are you
now going to sort of like put it on and run out
before actually the smoke goes out, because you can't actually be there
for that real full encounter? You will set it up but then
you have to leave. You're not able to fully be there for
the encounter. Or no, you actually want, once you're there and you've
done all the preparations, you want that smoke to go up right
away. You want to be present when that is happening. So I
think that's already a very fascinating debate there, but that's actually not
our focus, but right there there's very fascinating those two opinions and
what the various symbolisms might mean.
But the encounter has to be between. What? You can't see anything.
Well, right. What? And it also obscures the smoke.
Well, it's a puss through smoke is I think the whole idea.
I mean, you could argue the other way. You could argue that
by making the smoke go up it's making it a less intimate
encounter. By not having the smoke, you're there without the smoke. So,
yeah, I somehow see the כי בענן אראה על הכפורת Ki Be'anan
Eira'e Al Hakaporet which means the ענן הכבוד, Anan Hakavod, not the
ענן הקטורת, Anan Haktoret, which is how the צדוקים Tzadukim read it,
but still see that there's some linkage there. But yes, anyway we
could talk about that, about what the various symbolisms could be about
that. Let's first see what the גמרא Gemara is doing with this.
כדי שתהא עשנה ממהרת לבוא K'dei She'ashana Miaheret Lavoh וזו היא עבודה
קשה
שבמקדש. V'zu Hi Avoda Kasha Shebi'Mikdash. This was the hardest עבודה in
the מקדש. Mikdash. So again, whenever the גמרא Gemara says that, there's
the reaction: זו היא ותו לא? Zu Hi V'tu Lo? זו היא
עבודה קשה שבמקדש, Zu Hi Avoda Kasha Shebi'Mikdash, זו היא ותו לא?
Zu Hi V'tu Lo? What, this is the only hard one? ואיכא
מליקה, Ve'ika Melika, the cutting of the neck from behind with a
thumbnail, ואיכא קמיצה, Ve'ika Kemitsa, what we talked before about the smoothing
of the מנחה when it's this hard thing in your hand. אלא
זו היא עבודה קשה ממאה עבודות
שבמקדש. Ela Zu Hi Avoda Kasha Mime'ah Avodot Shebi'Mikdash. This is one
of the hardest עבודות in the מקדש. Mikdash. Nevertheless, what do you
see? The whole thing was describing how you get it from the
ladle back into your hands, how you do a חפינה a second
time. It would be so much easier if you could just pour
from the ladle straight on the fire, but you don't do that.
ושמע מינה חופין וחוזר וחופין, U'shma Mina Chofin V'chozer V'chofin, you see
pretty explicitly you've got to do another חפינה when you're in the
קדשי קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and you have to release it from your
hands. שמע מינה, Shma Mina, that we see.
Okay, so then, in order to do that, how did we just
prove it?
Yeah, I don't know, right. We didn't prove it from a פסוק.
Pasuk. Somehow it's from the tradition, you're right. I don't know, it's
assumed that מלוא חפניו Melo Chofnav means the מלוא חפניו Melo Chofnav
coming from the חפינה is going on, but it's not exactly clear.
So we know that you do another חפינה and therefore it raises
the question whether it has to be your חפינה that you're using
or somebody else could have done the חפינה and given it to
you or dropped dead and then you would have taken it over.
Yes.
The big problem with the fire is you've got this coal sitting
on the קדשי קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
On the floor, right.
On the floor and you come in and basically it's a pile
of incense sitting in the shovel basically. And now you come with
this חפינה handful to take it and put it down, there was
a possibility you could have put out the coals.
Well, that might
be, you mean according to the opinion that it's וצברה, V'tzavra, you
dump it down. Right. I don't know how the relative size, although
the גמרא did say sometimes the חפינה could be as big as
the quantity of the coals. I don't know. For people that have
worked on a grill, which would not be me, living in an
apartment, you know, you will know better than I.
It takes a lot of dirt to put out a fire of
hot coals.
Yeah, I mean this is a hand breadth and the other was
like three קבים. Kabim. Yeah, depending on how hot they are. Although
I will say that תוספות says one of the aspects that made
it עבודה קשה, Avoda Kasha, or maybe it was רש״י, Rashi, says
that you have to put it down without getting burnt yourself. When
you release something on fire and all the hot smoke comes up,
you know, you could get burnt, so that's also part of the
challenge.
Although the handle of the shovel doesn't have to be burnt, does
it?
Of the idea of get the smoke? Right, it has to produce
the smoke.
You just dump the coals, just dump them down, you're not going
to get smoke, you're going to get...
Yeah, I mean, if the fire goes out right away, it won't
be enough to create smoke.
All
right.
All right. Let's take a look. Now the גמרא continues. Okay. So
that's the חופן וחוזר וחופן. chofen ve-chozer ve-chofen. So, איבעיא להו. ibaia
lehu. Now that we're raising, now we get back to the other
question we raised:
שחט ומת. shachat u-meis. He shechted the פר, par, going back to
that, and then he died. So this was the issue we raised
before. Can you pick up with the blood or do you have
to have started
with the live cow?
And you did the קבלה kabbalah too, presumably?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. מאי? mai? מאי... mai... ומת. u-meis. מהו שיכנס אחר
בדמו? mahu she-yikanes acher be-damo? Can somebody else pick up with the
blood after the blood was caught? But do you have to, does
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol have to start with the live פר?
par? מי אמרינן בפר ואפילו בדמו של פר? mi amrinan be-par ve-afillu
be-damo shel par?
Maybe it says 'with the cow', that doesn't exclude the blood. It
says אהרן Aharon comes into the קודש kodesh with the פר, par,
it means with the blood that represents the פר. par. You don't
have to start with the live פר. par. או דלמא בפר ולא
בדמו של פר? o dilma be-par ve-lo be-damo shel par? No, it
says 'the cow' to mean you, the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, have
to start with the live one. If another כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
started with the live one, you can't pick up if it's dead.
So now it's a whole big debate. רבי חנינא אומר בפר ולא
בדמו של פר, Rabbi Chanina omer be-par ve-lo be-damo shel par, as
we saw a minute ago, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says you have
to start with the cow. And therefore, if he dropped dead like
with the קטורת, he said you've got to go back to the
beginning. If he dropped dead before the blood is done, you've got
to go back to the beginning, the next כהן. וריש לקיש אמר
בפר ואפילו בדמו של פר. ve-Reish Lakish amar be-par ve-afillu be-damo shel
par. No, if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol drops dead, another one
can pick up with the blood. You don't have to start with
the cow. רבי אמי אמר בפר ולא בדמו של פר, Rabbi Ami
amar be-par ve-lo be-damo shel par, you have to, the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol has to start with the live cow. רבי יצחק אמר
בפר ואפילו בדמו של פר. Rabbi Yitzchak amar be-par ve-afillu be-damo shel
par. No, the cow and even if the cow is dead, the
blood counts just as well. Okay, so we have a whole big
debate. I don't understand how this is possible. What's impossible? This I
don't understand how it's possible. What's impossible? Somebody here is doing the
stirring. He did the שחיטה, he did the קבלה. kabbalah. Somebody is
doing the stirring. He did the קבלה. kabbalah. Yeah, yeah, that's what
Michael asked. He did the קבלה, kabbalah, somebody is stirring. That was
my point. Right, somebody is stirring and then he drops dead. In
all these scenarios, I hope the guy who is doing all this
stirring has a strong forearm. Okay. איתיביה רבי אמי לרבי יצחק. iseiviah
Rabbi Ami le-Rabbi Yitzchak. So רבי אמי Rabbi Ami asked רבי יצחק.
Rabbi Yitzchak. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami said that it has to be
the cow itself. You have to start with the cow. לרבי יצחק
נפשא. le-Rabbi Yitzchak nafsha. נמנין ומושכין ידיהן ממנו עד שישחט. nimnin u-moshchin
yedeihen mimenu ad she-yishachet. We say by the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, going back to that, that people can join the group
or withdraw from the group until it gets shechted.
Which means that once it gets shechted, they can no longer join
the group. But now he says the following. This is fascinating.
You understand that this is not a local debate of how to
read the verse,
but how do you understand the blood of the sacrifice? Does that
blood still represent the animal? So if you're saying ואפילו בדמו של
פר, ve-afillu be-damo shel par, even though the פסוק pasuk says בזאת
יבא אהרן בפר, be-zos yavo Aharon be-par, it says you come with
the פר. par. If your response is, 'Yeah, but the blood represents
the ox, that's fine to start with it,' so the challenge is
going to be, you mean to tell me in all areas of
הלכה, halakhah, you can start with the blood and consider that to
be the animal itself? So if that's true, why can't I join
your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach after you shechted it? Don't say it's
already dead, what do I care? It's dead. You've got the blood
here. You haven't thrown the blood yet. It still represents the קרבן.
korban. Let me join in. Okay. ואי איתא, ve-i isa, if what
you're saying is right, עד שיזרק מיבעי ליה. ad she-yizarek mibei lei.
I should be allowed to join it until the blood is thrown
because the blood still represents the animal. So the גמרא says no.
שאני התם, shani hasam, there it's different. דכתיב מן השה. de-ksiv min
ha-seh. The פסוק pasuk says that if ימעט הבית, yim'at ha-bayis, if
the numbers are too little from its being from a שה. seh.
And from that we mean that we learn to mean you can
limit, you can lower the number of participants or raise the number
of participants when it is a שה. seh. מחיותא דשה. mi-chayusa de-seh.
As long as the שה seh is alive... a play on words,
חיות, chayus, חיותא, chayusa, a hey and a ches... as long as
the sheep is alive, you can change the number of participants. Now
I would have said what's funny is that that makes the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach the exception. I would have said different. I would
have said when does the blood represent the animal? You know, the
blood represents the animal when the focus is on the הקרבה hakravah
of the animal, on the offering of it as a קרבן. korban.
So yes, you throw the blood of the פסח, Pesach, but as
we've said before, the פסח Pesach doesn't sort of focus on the
blood as... that's not the focal point of the פסח. Pesach. Well,
maybe it was in מצרים.
Mitzrayim. Yeah. But anyway, to think about when
the
blood represents the animal might be different for different קרבנות. korbanos. Let's
read one more question about this where you'll see how far the
גמרא goes with the comparison. מתיב מר זוטרא. maseiv Mar Zutra. אין
פודין, ein podin, you
can't do a פדיון pidyon of פטר חמור, peter chamor, of the
firstborn of a donkey, לא ב... lo be... לא בעגל, lo be'egel,
not with a calf, because it has to be a sheep or
a goat. ולא בחיה, velo bechaya, not with a non-domesticated breed. ולא
בשחוטה, velo bishchuta, or a shechted sheep. ולא בטרפה, velo bitreifa, or
a sheep
that has a wound, is a treife. ולא בכלאים, velo bekhilayim, or
a crossbreed. ולא בכוי, velo vekhoy, another type of a koy. אלא
בשה, ela beseh, it has to be a sheep. So the question
is, why can't it be with a dead sheep? Why don't we
say the blood represents the thing itself? Now, there it seems to
be a crazy comparison, because there we're not even talking about a
קרבן. korban? When might I say the blood represents the animal when
we're talking about the blood having weight and going to be used
as a bringing of the קרבן? korban, You bring the blood, it's
like you bring the animal. Here we're talking about a dead sheep.
Why should I think that the blood is still considered like the
sheep is around? But the גמרא doesn't give that answer. As long
as it still has the blood, let the blood represent the sheep.
So the גמרא says no. שאני התם דיליף שה שה מפסח. shani
hatam dyalif seh seh mi-Pesach. No, there it's different. There it says
sheep and it says sheep by פסח. Pesach. The same way by
פסח Pesach it has to be alive, here it has to be
alive. Again,
what
we are saying now is this debate of whether you can pick
up with the blood is not just seen as a local question
of יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. It's translated as
a global question of the blood representing the animal itself. And what's
particularly shocking is that the גמרא doesn't even limit that to the
case of blood of a קרבן, korban, what really is like bringing
the life of the animal on the altar, and thinks that if
you say it by the קרבן, you can say it here by
a dead sheep by the פדיון פטר חמור. pidyon peter chamor. So
we will continue with this issue of the blood representing the animal
tomorrow.